A Finding Aid to the Ray Yoshida Papers, 1903-2010, bulk 1950-2005, in the Archives of American Art AAA.yoshray
Archives of American Art
Ray Yoshida papers
bulk 1950-2005
1903-2010
AAA.yoshray
Archives of American Art
9.1 Linear feet
The papers of Chicago artist and educator Ray Yoshida measure 9.1 linear feet and date from 1903 to 2010, with the bulk of the material dating from 1950 to 2005. Yoshida’s career as a painter and collagist as well as his long tenure as a professor at the School of the Art Institute of Chicago are documented through biographical material, personal correspondence, notebooks and writings, teaching records, personal business records, printed material, photographs, sketchbooks, artwork by Yoshida and others, and scrapbooks. Items within the collection also document Yoshida’s personal interest in collecting folk art and artifacts.
Yoshida, Ray
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated in 2012 by Ray Yoshida via Terri Yoho of the Kohler Foundation, representing Yoshida's estate, and in 2013 by Jennifer Sabas and Shayle Miller, estate executors.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington D.C. research facility. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice. One box of letters from Jim Nutt are ACCESS RESTRICTED; use requires written permission.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 11 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1950-2005 (0.5 Linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1954-2009 (2.0 Linear feet; Boxes 1-3, 9, 12)
Series 3: Notebooks, circa 1960s-1990s (0.5 Linear feet; Box 3)
Series 4: Writings, circa 1950-2001 (0.4 Linear feet; Boxes 3-4)
Series 5: Teaching Records, 1962-2003 (0.4 Linear feet; Box 4)
Series 6: Personal Business Records, circa 1971-2010 (0.6 Linear feet; Boxes 4-5)
Series 7: Printed Material, circa 1912-2005 (1.9 Linear feet; Boxes 5-6, 12)
Series 8: Photographs, circa 1911-1990s (0.4 Linear feet; Box 7)
Series 9: Sketchbooks, circa 1960s-2000s (0.9 Linear feet; Boxes 7, 10-11)
Series 10: Artwork, 1903-2000s (0.9 Linear feet; Boxes 7-8, 12)
Series 11: Scrapbooks, early 1900s-1960s (0.6 Linear feet; Boxes 8-11)
Biographical/Historical note
Ray Yoshida (1930-2009) was a painter, collagist, and educator in Chicago, Illinois.
Raymond Kakuo Yoshida was born in Kapaa, Hawaii, in 1930. He attended the University of Hawaii for two years and completed a B.A. in Arts Education at the Art Institute of Chicago in 1953. He also served in the U.S. Army for two years during the Korean War. In 1957 he recieved his M.F.A from Syracuse University and became a faculty member at the School of the Art Institute of Chicago in 1959. He was named Frank Harold Sellers Professor in the Department of Painting and Drawing in 1971, retired as professor emeritus in 1998, and continued to teach until 2003.
Yoshida's paintings and collages were strongly influenced by comics as well as his own collection of folk and outsider art. He regularly exhibited at Phyllis Kind Gallery in Chicago from 1975 to 1996, and a major retrospective of his work was organized by the Contemporary Museum of Honolulu in 1998. He retired to Hawaii in 2005 where he lived until his death in 2009.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of Chicago artist and educator Ray Yoshida measure 9.1 linear feet and date from 1903 to 2010, with the bulk of the material dating from 1950 to 2005. Yoshida’s career as a painter and collagist as well as his long tenure as a professor at the School of the Art Institute of Chicago are documented through biographical material, personal correspondence, notebooks and writings, teaching records, personal business records, printed material, photographs, sketchbooks, artwork by Yoshida and others, and scrapbooks. Items within the collection also document Yoshida’s personal interest in collecting folk art and artifacts.
Art Institute of Chicago. -- Faculty; Art--Study and teaching; Collagists--Illinois--Chicago; Educators--Illinois--Chicago; Folk art--Collectors and collecting; Painters--Illinois--Chicago; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks
- Biographical Material, 1950-2005; Series 1; 0.5 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Found here is biographical documentation about Ray Yoshida, including award certificates, identification records, student records, and three interview transcripts. Also found is one video recording of a documentary short about Yoshida’s art and object collection at his Chicago home.
  - Biographical Summaries and Resumes, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Calendars, 2001-2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - College Art Association Award, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Diploma, Syracuse University, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Documentary Short, "The Individuality of the Inanimate Object", 1990; 2 Videocassettes (VHS) Duplicates; 1 Videocassettes (U-matic) (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Drivers License Application, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Health Documents, 1998; 2005 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Interview Transcript, circa 1982 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Interview Transcript, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Interview Transcript, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Membership Cards, 1973; 2003 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Passport, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Rockford College Yearbook, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Student Term Records, 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence, 1954-2009; Series 2; 2 Linear feet Boxes 1-3, 9, 12
  Correspondence is primarily of a personal nature and includes numerous letters, postcards, and greeting cards from friends, colleagues, and artists, including Roger Brown, Jim Nutt, Gladys Nilsson, Art Green, Christina Ramberg, Karl Wirsum, Miyoko Ito, Jin Soo Kim, Barbara Rossi, Vera Berdich, and Tom Kapsalis among others. Some letters are illustrated.
  Arrangement note
  Correspondence is arranged in chronological order by year. Undated correspondence is unsorted. Access restricted letters from Jim Nutt are arranged in a separate container.
  - Letters from Roger Brown, 1968-1990s (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1954-1969 (Box 1, Folder 17-21)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1982 (Box 1, Folder 22-35)
  - Correspondence, 1983-2009 (Box 2, Folder 1-27)
  - Undated Correspondence, circa 1960s-2000s (Box 2, Folder 28-29)
  - Undated Correspondence, circa 1960s-2000s (Box 3, Folder 1-7)
  - Draft Outgoing Letters, circa 2005 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Letters from Jim Nutt (ACCESS RESTRICTED), circa 1968-1970 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Letter from Glen Davies, 1973 (Box 12, Folder 1)
- Notebooks, circa 1960s-1990s; Series 3; 0.5 Linear feet Box 3
  Notebooks contain notes on art history, art technique, Japanese language, travel, and other subjects. Many of the notebooks include sketches and contain loose items such as news clippings.
  - Japanese Lessons Notebook, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Notebook on Enamels, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Notebook, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Notebook, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Notebook, undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Notebook, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Notebook, circa 1960-1964 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Notebook, circa 1960s (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Notebook, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Travel Notebook, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 18)
- Writings, circa 1950-2001; Series 4; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 3-4
  Found here are Ray Yoshida's writings for college courses, fragments of writings on art and other subjects, and notes. Notes consist of lists, ideas, travel plans, and teaching material. Writings by others include essays by Yoshida’s students, draft essays for exhibitions, and poetry by Susan Wheeler.
  - Course Assignments, 1950s (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous Writing Fragments, undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Notes, circa 1960s-2000s (Box 3, Folder 21-23)
  - Travel Notes, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Poetry by Susan Wheeler, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Writings about Ray Yoshida, circa 1998 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Writings by Norman Coggeshall, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Writings by Others, circa 1960s-2001 (Box 4, Folder 5-7)
- Teaching Records, 1962-2003; Series 5; 0.4 Linear feet Box 4
  Teaching records primarily document Yoshida’s tenure as a professor at the School of the Art Institute of Chicago, though a few records of guest professorships at other schools are included. These records are not comprehensive, but include a few course evaluations, employment records, teaching notes, and photocopies of research material. Also found are numerous letters of recommendation he wrote for students. Miscellaneous teaching records are unsorted and include department memos, planning documents, course summaries and curriculum, correspondence, and notes.
  - Course Evaluations, 1985-1986 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Employment Records, 1967-2003 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Letters of Recommendation, 1962-2002 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
  - Teaching Notes and Research Material, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Miscellaneous, 1960s-2000 (Box 4, Folder 13-19)
- Personal Business Records, circa 1971-2010; Series 6; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 4-5
  Found here is documentation regarding the sale, exhibition, and loan of artwork by Ray Yoshida, including his business dealings with the Phyllis Kind Gallery. Also found are business cards and address lists, a few business receipts, and a National Endowment for the Arts application. Additionally there are several files regarding the estate of artist Roger Brown and the establishment of the Roger Brown Study Center at the School of the Art Institute of Chicago.
  - Artwork Sales, 1981-1984 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Business Cards and Contact Lists, undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Catalog Cards for Museum Objects, undated (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Estate of (James) Roger Brown, 1997-2002 (Box 4, Folder 23-29)
  - Exhibition, Abstract/Symbol/Image, 1984-1986 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Exhibition, Made in Chicago, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Exhibition, Ray Yoshida Retrospective, Contemporary Museum, Honolulu, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Exhibition, Ray Yoshida Retrospective, Madison Art Center, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Home Improvement, 1995-2001 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Loan Agreements, circa 1990-2010 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Loan to Minnesota Museum of American Art, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - National Endowment for the Arts Fellowship Application, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Phyllis Kind Gallery, 1975; 1980-1998 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Receipts, 1971-2010 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Printed Material, circa 1912-2005; Series 7; 1.9 Linear feet Boxes 5-6, 12
  Printed material includes published documentation about Yoshida’s career as an artist as well as items collected by Yoshida as source material or for personal interest. Found here are exhibition catalogs, invitations, and announcements, as well as news clippings, magazines, newsletters and press releases documenting his career. Collected printed material includes postcards, comics and comic books, mail order catalogs, magazines, product labels, and advertisements. Also found are many small clippings from comics collected for collages.
  - Antiques Guides (Annotated), circa 1995-1996 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Clippings for Collages, undated (Box 5, Folder 7-12)
  - Clippings of Comics, undated (Box 5, Folder 13-16)
  - Collected Postcards, 1912-1994 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Comic Books, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements, 1960s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 19-22)
  - Exhibition and Event Announcements, 1950s-1990s (Box 5, Folder 23-24)
  - Farm Journal, 1919-1921 (Box 5, Folder 25-26)
  - Japanese Publications, circa 1990s (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Magazines, circa 1950s (Box 5, Folder 28-29)
  - Mail Order Catalog, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, circa 1970s-2000s (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - News Clippings, 1950s-2000s (Box 6, Folder 3-17)
    Oversized material housed in Box 12, Folder 2
  - Newsletters and Magazines, 1960-2001; 1916 (Box 6, Folder 18-20)
  - Press Releases, 1979-1996 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Product Labels and Advertising, circa 1940s-1980s (Box 6, Folder 22-23)
  - Recipe Books, circa 1910s (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Reproductions of Artwork by Others, undated (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Wallpaper Sample Book, circa 1950s (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Wholesale Catalog, 1917 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Oversized News Clippings from Box 6, Folders 3-17, circa 1960s-2005 (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Photographs, circa 1911-1990s; Series 8; 0.4 Linear feet Box 7
  Photographs depict Ray Yoshida, friends, students, travel, and artwork. Also found are a few photographs of Karl Wirsum’s studio, as well as photographs of various subjects collected by Yoshida. Additionally, there is one photograph album from the early 1910s with photographs depicting a young woman with her friends and family.
  - Photographs of Ray Yoshida, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Personal Photographs, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 7, Folder 2-6)
  - Negatives, Photographs of Travel, circa 1970s (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Photographs of Karl Wirsum's Studio, circa 1971 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Slides of Artwork, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Transparencies of Artwork, undated (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Collected Photographs, circa 1910s-1960s (Box 7, Folder 12-14)
  - Photograph Album, circa 1911-1913 (Box 7, Folder 15)
- Sketchbooks, circa 1960s-2000s; Series 9; 0.9 Linear feet Boxes 7, 10-11
  Sketchbooks include pencil and ink sketches of various subjects. A few also include loose items such as notes and news clippings. Most sketchbooks appear to contain sketches by Yoshida, but researchers should note that it is possible that some sketchbooks belonged to students or other artists.
  - Sketchbook, circa 1960s (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Sketchbooks, undated (Box 7, Folder 17-25)
  - Sketchbooks, circa 1960s; undated (Box 10, Folder 1-5)
  - Sketchbooks, undated; circa 1966 (Box 11, Folder 1-3)
- Artwork, 1903-2000s; Series 10; 0.9 Linear feet Boxes 7-8, 12
  Artwork by Ray Yoshida includes collages on paper, pencil sketches, and ink drawings. Artworks by others include numerous prints by Kathleen Blackshear, Ethel Spears, and Vivian Mayers, and collages, drawings, and prints given to Yoshida by students and friends. Other artwork appears to have been created by children, including handmade picture books, alphabet books, and paper collages. A few items such as hand-painted photographs and painted puzzle pieces were made by an unidentified artist, possibly Yoshida.
  - Artwork by Ray Yoshida, circa 1990s (Box 7, Folder 26)
    Oversized material housed in Box 12, Folder 3
  - Drawings by Ray Yoshida, undated (Box 7, Folder 27-28)
    Oversized material housed in Box 12, Folder 4
  - Hand-colored Photographs, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Painted Puzzle Pieces, undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Artwork by Kathleen Blackshear, Ethel Spears, and Vivian Mayers, undated (Box 8, Folder 3-4)
  - Artist Book by Jacob Hashimoto, 1996 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Child's Handmade Picture Book, 1903 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Unidentified Artist, Number Book, circa 1930s (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Unidentified Artist, Voodoo Kit, undated (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Unidentified Artist, Alphabet Book, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Artwork by Others, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 10-16)
  - Oversized Comic Collages by Ray Yoshida from Box 7, Folder 26, undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Drawings by Ray Yoshida from Box 7, Folders 27-28, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
- Scrapbooks, early 1900s-1960s; Series 11; 0.6 Linear feet Boxes 8-11
  Found here are six scrapbooks. Three of the scrapbooks containing source images, clippings, and comics appear to have been created by Yoshida. Three additional scrapbooks were created by others and collected by Yoshida. Included is a child’s scrapbook containing many clippings about the Dionne quintuplets, a scrapbook from the early 1900s containing clippings and ephemera, and a detailed travel scrapbook created by Edward and Edna Hillier.
  - Scrapbook, early 1900s (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Child's Scrapbook, circa 1936-1937 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Scrapbook of Source Images, circa 1960s (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Scrapbook of Clippings, circa 1971 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Edward and Edna Hillier Scrapbook, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Scrapbook of Comics, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)